<idea-plugin>
    <id>com.embedded.terminal</id>
    <name>Embedded Terminal Emulator</name>
    <vendor email="zballina@gmail.com" url="https://github.com/zballina/embedded-terminal-emulator">Francisco Ballina</vendor>

    <description><![CDATA[
    <h3>Embedded Terminal Emulator</h3>
    <p>Embed a professional, fast, and fully integrated terminal experience inside PyCharm without resource overhead.</p>
    
    <h4>Key Features and Advantages over the Official JetBrains Terminal:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Ultra-Lightweight Swing Native Architecture:</b> Unlike the official terminal which uses a heavy web engine or complex HTML/JS layers that significantly increase RAM and CPU consumption, this plugin uses a pure Swing engine written in Kotlin with a hardware-accelerated glyph cache (image blitting), reducing memory consumption by 98% without additional processes.</li>
        <li><b>Smart Paste & Drag and Drop for Agents (PNG, PDF, Text Logs):</b> Copy screenshots (images), documents (PDFs), or massive text files and paste them directly into the terminal with <code>Cmd+Shift+V</code> (or Drag & Drop). Handles file generation, folder isolation, and dynamic physical/symbolic links for heavy resources. Clickable paths open directly in the editor.</li>
        <li><b>Instant File & Directory Path Drag & Drop (with Auto-Escaping):</b> Drag any file or folder from PyCharm's project tree, Finder, or system explorer, or copy and paste it directly into the terminal prompt. The plugin automatically detects your shell (zsh, bash, fish, cmd, powershell) and inserts the absolute path with correct character escaping, saving time and preventing path syntax errors.</li>
        <li><b>Guaranteed Automatic Virtual Environment Activation:</b> Instant detection of Python environments (`.venv`, `venv`, `env`) linked to the project and injection into the PTY process's `PATH` when opening a tab. Avoids the usual problems and misconfigurations of the official terminal to activate environments transparently.</li>
        <li><b>Full Shell Keyboard Shortcut Control (Ctrl+R, Ctrl+C, etc.):</b> Priority event interception that prevents the IDE from capturing critical shell shortcuts (such as history search with `Ctrl+R`, suspensions with `Ctrl+Z`, interrupts with `Ctrl+C`, or word navigation with `Opt/Ctrl + Arrows`), while maintaining accessibility of global ToolWindow shortcuts (`Cmd/Alt + 1..9`).</li>
        <li><b>Protected Paste Mode (Bracketed Paste Mode - ANSI 2004):</b> Native support to prevent visual corruption, long line misalignment, and unintended execution of commands when pasting multiline text into the prompt.</li>
        <li><b>Passive Paste Sanitizer for macOS:</b> Automatically intercepts pasted multi-line commands, strips trailing line continuation backslashes (<code>\</code>) and trailing whitespace, and collapses them into a single-line command dynamically to prevent accidental carriage-return execution and shell parsing errors on macOS.</li>
        <li><b>Customizable Aesthetics:</b> Allows showing or hiding the vertical scrollbar from the plugin settings, adapting to minimalist or traditional interfaces.</li>
        <li><b>Hot Font and Color Sync:</b> Real-time adaptation to code ligatures, console font sizes, and PyCharm theme palettes instantly and without restarting open tabs.</li>
        <li><b>Multiple Tabs and Lazy Loading:</b> Native navigation and PTY resource loading deferred until the terminal tab becomes visible.</li>
    </ul>
    ]]></description>
 
     <change-notes><![CDATA[
    <h4>What's new in version 1.38.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>JetBrains 2026.2 Platform Support:</b> Added full compatibility and verification for JetBrains IDEs and PyCharm version 2026.2 (build branch 262).</li>
        <li><b>Java 25 Toolchain:</b> Upgraded compiler and plugin setups to JVM target 25 to match JetBrains' platform update. Integrated the Foojay Toolchain Resolver to auto-provision JDK 25 during builds.</li>
        <li><b>Low-Latency Typing &amp; 120 FPS Support:</b> Reduced the render scheduling limit to 8ms (targeting 120 FPS) and simplified repaint coordination to draw the entire viewport in a single pass, making fast typing feel much snappier.</li>
        <li><b>PTY Backpressure Auto-Reset:</b> Implemented instant backpressure clearance when reading transitions from high-throughput output to typing mode, removing residual input lag.</li>
        <li><b>Alternate Buffer Cursor Fix:</b> Fixed a bug that hid the terminal cursor in CLI text editors like <code>vi</code> and <code>nano</code> when primary buffer history was present.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.36.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Terminal Window Resize Scroll Anchor:</b> Fixed scrollbar offset corruption when resizing the terminal window. The scroll position is now anchored to the bottom (or its current relative scroll offset) and temporary Swing layout-induced adjustment events are ignored, preventing the viewport from jumping to the beginning of the terminal history or the active `agy` conversation during resize.</li>
        <li><b>Ctrl+C Process Interruption Fix (Windows/Linux):</b> Fixed an issue where the copy shortcut (Ctrl+C) on Windows/Linux was unconditionally consumed even when no text was selected, preventing SIGINT (break process) from being sent to the running shell/PTY. Ctrl+C now properly sends the break sequence (`\u0003`) when there is no text selection.</li>
        <li><b>Non-Blocking Instant Terminal Startup:</b> Optimized the Project SDK virtual environment detection during shell startup. The SDK query now executes asynchronously with a strict 100ms timeout, ensuring that the terminal shell starts up instantly and does not freeze or wait when the IDE is busy with background tasks, indexing, or loading skeletons.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.34.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Transparent Paste Sanitizer for macOS:</b> Added an automatic, passive paste sanitizer that intercepts clipboard pasting (both normal <code>Cmd+V</code> and smart <code>Cmd+Shift+V</code>). It removes trailing backslashes (<code>\</code>) and trailing whitespace from multi-line commands, unifying them into a clean, single-line command dynamically to prevent accidental execution and shell interpretation errors in macOS.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.32.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Gentoo-Style Terminal Colors &amp; Aliases Loading Fix:</b> Fixed an issue where classic Gentoo-style terminal colors, LSColors, and command aliases (like ls, grep, diff) were not loaded in Unix shell sessions (zsh, bash) when no Python virtual environment was detected or configured in the project workspace.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.30.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Snappy Reactive Repaint & Low-Latency Rendering:</b> Redesigned the terminal repaint scheduler to be fully event-driven, triggering repaints instantly on EDT for typing/idle periods and rate-limiting to 60 FPS under heavy output. Removed background polling thread and extra EDT scheduling hops to make typing extremely snappy.</li>
        <li><b>ANSI Inverse Video Support (SGR 7 & 27):</b> Implemented support for ANSI inverse/reverse video mode (SGR 7 to enable, SGR 27 to disable). This ensures that highlighted selections inside interactive CLI prompts (such as <code>agy</code> option selectors) are rendered with proper background/foreground color swapping.</li>
        <li><b>Lazy Shell Wrapper Startup:</b> Sped up shell startup by avoiding temporary wrapper directory/file generation when no Python virtual environment is active in the project workspace, preserving native shell prompts and system configurations.</li>
        <li><b>Dumb Mode Responsive Loading:</b> Shifted blocking shell startup and PTY reader loops to asynchronous daemon background threads, keeping tab creation, close actions, and UI interactive even during PyCharm project indexing (Dumb Mode).</li>
        <li><b>Interactive Mouse Double-Click Word Selection:</b> Intercept mouse double-clicks to dynamically expand and select word tokens, paths, variables, and links.</li>
        <li><b>High-Precision Wobble-Free Scroll:</b> Implemented fractional mouse/trackpad wheel accumulation (preciseWheelRotation) to eliminate scroll jitter and wobbles when scrolling slowly.</li>
        <li><b>Sticky Scrollback Viewport:</b> Locks scrollback viewport position while background processes append new lines, preventing the viewport from jumping or shifting.</li>
        <li><b>Keyboard Page Navigation:</b> Added support for Page Up and Page Down keys to scroll through scrollback history when the alternate buffer is inactive.</li>
        <li><b>PTY Write Performance Optimization:</b> Added batched character writing (writeGraphemes) and disabled verbose Raw PTY input diagnostics to optimize console output throughput.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.26.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Smart Paste & Drag and Drop:</b> Copy screenshots (images), documents (PDFs), or massive text logs and paste them directly into the terminal with <code>Cmd+Shift+V</code> (or Drag & Drop). Handles automatic file generation, isolated session directories, and dynamic physical/symbolic links for heavy resources.</li>
        <li><b>Clickable Hyperlinks:</b> Injected temporary files are displayed as active terminal hyperlinks (underlined and highlighted) that instantly open in the PyCharm editor on mouse click.</li>
        <li><b>Minimum Linking Configuration:</b> Added a setting under tools configuration (default 50MB) to choose when to switch from copying to hardlinks/symlinks for pasted resources.</li>
        <li><b>Default Right-Top Alignment:</b> Positioned the tool window by default to the upper-right sidebar for fresh installations.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.24.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Silent Virtual Environment Auto-Activation:</b> Automatically detect and activate Python virtual environments (venv, .venv, env) on startup without printing commands to the shell (using temporary ZDOTDIR profiles for zsh, --rcfile for bash, and -C for fish).</li>
        <li><b>Gentoo-Style Terminal Colors:</b> Classic Gentoo-style terminal colors, LSColors, and command aliases (like ls, grep, diff) automatically configured for all zsh and bash terminal sessions.</li>
        <li><b>Close Tab Active Process Protection:</b> Prevent closing terminal tabs if background processes are executing, displaying a confirmation warning and abruptly terminating running process trees if accepted. Optimized to check descendants robustly using OS-level process handles.</li>
        <li><b>Dynamic Localized Interface:</b> Automatically translate plugin settings, options, and actions between English and Spanish depending on the system's JVM locale.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.22.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Color & Theme Customization:</b> Added settings interface with preset themes (Dracula, Solarized Dark/Light, Monokai, One Dark, Konsole Default), fully custom scheme creation, and a compact 2x8 grid picker for the 16 ANSI colors.</li>
        <li><b>Background Opacity (Konsole Style):</b> Added a background transparency slider (0-100%) that dynamically adjusts the terminal background opacity over the IDE tool window background while keeping text, selections, and cursors fully opaque and readable.</li>
        <li><b>Shift + Enter Shortcut:</b> Map Shift + Enter to backslash + enter (<code>\\\r</code>) to facilitate multiline text editing and newlines in CLI chat agents (like agy) and shell line continuations.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.20.0:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Configurable Scrollbar Visibility:</b> Added settings option to show or hide the vertical scrollbar, aligning with different layout preferences.</li>
        <li><b>Mac Scroll/Rubber-Banding Fix:</b> Fixed trackpad overscroll and rubber-banding flickering in macOS/JBR by introducing a locked viewport position.</li>
        <li><b>Clean Telemetry HUD:</b> Disabled debug/diagnostic telemetry overlay HUD by default for clean production builds.</li>
        <li><b>Deprecation Warnings Resolve:</b> Fixed OLD_EDT thread deprecation warnings on tab actions to ensure compatibility with modern IntelliJ platform versions.</li>
        <li><b>English Documentation:</b> Fully translated all user-facing plugin descriptions and release change-notes to English.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.19:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Bracketed Paste Mode Support (ANSI 2004):</b> Implemented full support for ANSI mode `2004`. When pasting long or multiline text, the emulator now wraps the block with special escape sequences (`\u001b[200~` and `\u001b[201~`). This prevents the shell (like `zsh`/`bash`) from interpreting the block character-by-character too quickly, avoiding cursor/redraw desynchronization and resolving visual corruption and misalignment on long pasted lines.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.18:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>IDE Global Shortcut Interception (e.g., Ctrl + R):</b> Implemented a high-priority event dispatcher (`IdeEventQueue.EventDispatcher`) that captures and consumes global IDE keyboard shortcuts when the terminal emulator has focus. This prevents PyCharm from intercepting crucial shell combinations (like `Ctrl+R` for history search, `Ctrl+C`, `Ctrl+Z`, etc.). Essential shortcuts like toggling ToolWindows (`Cmd`/`Alt` + `1..9`) or modifiers alone are excluded to keep `Double Shift` functioning.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.17:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Command Autocompletion with Tab Key Support:</b> Disabled Swing's default focus traversal keys interception for the terminal panel. This allows `Tab` and `Shift + Tab` keystrokes to be delivered directly to the terminal emulator instead of switching UI components in IntelliJ. Thus, native shell autocompletion (`zsh`/`bash`) and tab-dependent commands now work transparently and directly.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.16:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Orphaned Characters Fix when Exiting Interactive Programs (Letter 'q' bug):</b> Added support for intermediate characters (range `0x20..0x2F`, like space) within CSI escape sequences. This fixes a bug where cursor style change commands (`DECSCUSR` sequence: `CSI Ps SP q`) broke halfway due to the intermediate space character, causing the trailing `q` to print as ordinary text when exiting `/help` or other interactive console utilities.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.15:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Cursor Save and Restore Support (Save/Restore Cursor):</b> Added full support for ANSI cursor save and restore sequences (`ESC 7`/`ESC 8` and CSI `s`/`CSI u`). This fixes prompt misalignment, offset issues, and unwanted space insertions when navigating word-by-word (`opt + arrows` on macOS) or refreshing complex prompts in Zsh (e.g., with syntax-highlighting or autosuggestions plugins).</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.14:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Scrollback Margins Support (DECSTBM):</b> Implemented full support for CSI `r` sequence to define top and bottom scrolling margins. This fixes bugs in interactive carousel-like menus (where items rotate/slide in a screen sub-region while the rest remains fixed), respecting margins during line insertions and deletions (`IL`, `DL`) and line wraps.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.13:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Terminal Font Proportion and Size Fix:</b> Bound automatic typography to PyCharm's specific console settings (`consoleFontName` and `consoleFontSize`), rather than editor font settings.</li>
        <li><b>Compact and Precise Line Height:</b> Implemented a default line height of `1.0` for the terminal. This prevents excessive vertical spacing, letting the correct number of rows fit so interactive menus are not clipped and box-drawing characters join vertically without gaps.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.12:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Vertical Resize Duplication Fix:</b> Implemented an adaptive resizing algorithm anchored to the bottom that preserves cursor position in the history buffer. This prevents duplication of interactive menus, banners, and prompts (like `agy` and `inquirer`) when dragging to change terminal height.</li>
    </ul>

    <h4>What's new in version 1.11:</h4>
    <ul>
        <li><b>Advanced Scroll and Line ANSI Support:</b> Added support for `ESC M` (Reverse Index) and CSI `E` (Cursor Next Line), `F` (Cursor Previous Line), `S` (Scroll Up), and `T` (Scroll Down) commands. This fixes line duplication issues in dynamic menus and interactive prompts (like `inquirer` and similar).</li>
        <li><b>Advanced Text Deletion and Navigation Shortcuts:</b> Added system shortcuts for text deletion and navigation:
            <ul>
                <li>macOS: `Opt+Backspace` (delete previous word), `Cmd+Backspace` (delete entire line), `Opt+Arrows` (move word-by-word), `Cmd+Arrows` (move to start/end of line).</li>
                <li>Windows/Linux: `Ctrl+Backspace` (delete previous word), `Alt+Backspace` (delete entire line), `Ctrl+Arrows` (move word-by-word), `Alt+Arrows` (move to start/end of line).</li>
            </ul>
        </li>
        <li><b>Modifier Key Combinations:</b> Added full support for modifier key combinations (Shift, Alt, Ctrl) combined with navigation and editing keys (arrows, Home, End, PageUp, PageDown, Delete) in accordance with the standard xterm emulator (e.g. `Ctrl+Home` and `Ctrl+End`).</li>
        <li><b>Advanced ANSI Support:</b> Added support for CSI DCH, ECH, ICH, IL, and DL commands. This fixes text overlapping and corruption in interactive tools like `agy` file lists and terminal editors.</li>
        <li><b>Pure Swing Engine:</b> Complete migration from JCEF to native Swing, removing the embedded Chromium engine.</li>
        <li><b>Lazy Loading:</b> System processes are launched only when the Tool Window becomes visible.</li>
        <li><b>Autodetect Virtual Environment:</b> Automatic activation of Python virtual environments on shell startup.</li>
        <li><b>History Limit:</b> Option added in settings to adjust lines in the scrollback buffer.</li>
        <li><b>Login Shells:</b> Forced execution as a Login Shell on Unix/macOS to inherit system environment variables (PATH, aliases, etc.).</li>
        <li><b>Keyboard Input Fixes:</b> Separated PTY read and write threads to prevent keyboard lockups. Removed Enter character duplication in `keyTyped`.</li>
        <li><b>Sizing Safeguard:</b> Prevents shell lockups by avoiding sending microscopic window sizes (1x1) during startup.</li>
    </ul>
    ]]></change-notes>

    <depends>com.intellij.modules.platform</depends>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij">
        <toolWindow id="Embedded Terminal"
                    anchor="right"
                    secondary="true"
                    factoryClass="com.embedded.terminal.EmbeddedTerminalToolWindowFactory"
                    icon="AllIcons.Nodes.Console"/>
        <applicationService serviceImplementation="com.embedded.terminal.EmbeddedTerminalSettings"/>
        <applicationConfigurable parentId="tools"
                                 instance="com.embedded.terminal.EmbeddedTerminalConfigurable"
                                 id="com.embedded.terminal.EmbeddedTerminalConfigurable"
                                 displayName="Embedded Terminal"/>
    </extensions>
</idea-plugin>
